<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A necessary and seasonable testimony against toleration and the present proceedings of sectaries and their abettors in England in reference to religion and government, with an admonition and exhortation unto their brethren there, from the Commissioners of the Kirk of Scotland. As also the return of the Estates of the Parliament of Scotland thereupon, concurring with the said testimony, and manifesting, that all the members of Parliament have upon their solemn oath disclaimed the knowledge of, or accession to the proceedings of the English army, against his Majesty or the members of Parliament in England, Jan. 18. 1648[/]9. Together also with a letter from the said Commissioners to the ministers in the Province of London, of the same date. Allowed of and entred according to order.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89867</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865061</idno>
  <idno type="VID">164912</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240903873</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing N366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E541_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205784</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865061</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865061e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89867)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164912)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E541[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A necessary and seasonable testimony against toleration and the present proceedings of sectaries and their abettors in England in reference to religion and government, with an admonition and exhortation unto their brethren there, from the Commissioners of the Kirk of Scotland. As also the return of the Estates of the Parliament of Scotland thereupon, concurring with the said testimony, and manifesting, that all the members of Parliament have upon their solemn oath disclaimed the knowledge of, or accession to the proceedings of the English army, against his Majesty or the members of Parliament in England, Jan. 18. 1648[/]9. Together also with a letter from the said Commissioners to the ministers in the Province of London, of the same date. Allowed of and entred according to order.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
                  <author>Ker, A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Tho Underhill at the Bible in Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 13 signed: A. Ker.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Jan. 18 1648"; the "9" in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Freedom of religion --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164912:1"/>
            <p>A Necessary and Seasonable TESTIMONY AGAINST TOLERATION And the present proceedings of <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and their Abettors in <hi>England</hi> in reference to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> with an Admonition and Exhortation unto their Brethren there, from the <hi>Commissioners of the Kirk of</hi> SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO The return of the Estates of the <hi>Parliament of Scotland</hi> thereupon, concurring with the said <hi>Testimony,</hi> and manifesting, that all the Members of <hi>Parliament</hi> have upon their solemn oath disclaimed the knowledge of, or accession to the proceedings of the English Army, against his MAJESTY or the <hi>Members of Parliament in England,</hi> Jan. 18. 1648/9.</p>
            <p>Together also with a letter from the said Commissioners to the Ministers in the Province of <hi>London,</hi> of the same date.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license" subtype="order">
                        <p>Allowed of and entred according to Order.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Tho Ʋnderhill</hi> at the Bible in Woodstreet. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:164912:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:164912:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinb.</hi>
                  <date>17. Ianuary 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>A Necessary and Seasonable TESTIMONY Against Toleration and the present Proceedings of Sectaries and their Abettors in <hi>England,</hi> in reference to Religion and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, with an Admonition and Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation unto their Brethren there, <hi>From the Commissioners of the Kirk of</hi> Scotland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit the work of Reformation in these Kingdoms hath engraven upon it so many and so lively cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of the truth and power and wisdom of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, as gives unto us sufficient grounds of hope that he will bring forth the head-stone of his house with shouting unto the shame of his adversaries and refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his people: Yet the sense which we have of our duty in regard of our station and trust, the dangers that threaten Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Government, together with the desire which we have to restore those that are fallen, to strengthen the weak, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the afflicted in <hi>England,</hi> cals upon us to give publique Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony against the present proceedings of Sectaries and their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors in that land, and to speak a word of admonition and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to our Brethren there.</p>
            <p>It hath been unto us, and we make no doubt unto the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Churches abroad, matter of much sorrow and grief of heart,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:164912:3"/>that after so many sufferings from, and wrastlings with the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish, Prelaticall and Malignant party; and after that they are brought down by the mighty hand and outstretched Arme of the Lord, there should arise in their stead any other to oppose his work in these Kingdoms; and it adds unto our affliction that they be such as professe for Jesus Christ, and pretend unto holinesse, and seemed once to build with our selves, whilest now their way is become grievous and goes down unto the gates of death, as tending to overturn Religion, destroy the League and Covenant, and to raze the foundations of Government.</p>
            <p>It shall not now be needfull to fall upon an enumeration of all these errours which have sprung up in <hi>England</hi> of late, a few years past have brought forth moe and more dangerous opinions in that one Kingdom, then many preceding generations in all the Churches of Christ, so evil and bitter a thing it is to leave every man to his own fancy, and the vineyard of the Lord without an hedge. The late generall Assemblies of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and their Commissioners have born Testimony against Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, Erastianism, Antinomianism, Anabaptism, Arminianism, Socinianism, Familism, Sceptism, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Ministers of the Province of <hi>London,</hi> and many others have more particularly reckoned and condemned the errours which men of corrupt mindes there have run unto. We blesse the Lord for every faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full witnesse, and desires to put to our seal, that his Testimony is true, but of all things it most afflicts our spirits, and we cannot but look upon it with horrour and amazement, that in a land Covenanted with God, after satan hath been so cunning as to sow the seed of so many heresies and errours, he should now prevail so far upon the spirits of men, as to make them instrumentall to plead for a Toleration unto all errours, and to endeavour that this monstrous iniquity may be established by a Law, and that of so large extent as carries no exception, but of expresse Popery and compulsive waies. The first whereof leaves latitude enough to tolerate any Papist whatsoever, if he can but a little dissemble the grosnesse of his way, and the later doth not obscurely point at those who plead for the Government of Jesus Christ by Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and hold that all men are to walk according to the rule of the word of God: Is this all the favour and approbation that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:164912:3"/>such may expect, to be ranked with the worst of Papists? There are many devices in the heart of man, but the Councel of the Lord shall stand, and he shall give unto his people a nail in his holy place.</p>
            <p>We have searched after the minde of Christ, and have traced the footsteps of the Prophets and Apostles in the old and new Testament, and no where can we finde in the Scriptures of truth, either precept or president allowed of God for Toleration of any errour: Much lesse did it ever come in his minde, or did he speak to any of his servants concerning a Toleration of all errour. As that infinite glorious divine essence is one in himself, most holy, most righteous, most true, so hath he given unto the children of men one eternall unchangeable law; according to the rule whereof they are to square their profession and order their conversation. Therefore as his justice requires in the Covenant of works that we should walk according thereunto, without declining to the right hand or the left, so he in his mercy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseth in the Covenant of grace to give unto his people, one heart and one way to fear him for ever, and in both Covenants they are obliged to walk after the rule of this law. It is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by many of those with whom we have now to doe, that no liberty is to be allowed unto men in the breaches of the duties of the second Table which we owe unto our neighbours, but that if a man sin against his neighbour and disturb the peace of the Common-wealth, he is to be restrained and punished. Can there any solid reason be given why it should not also be thus in regard of the duties of the first Table which we owe unto God? Is not one Lord authour of both? Hath not conscience influence on both? Is not the Lords glory interressed in the one as well as in the other? Doth not his Image shine as brightly, and may it not as much be defaced in the one as in the other? Are the things of God lesse pretious then the things of men? And that which concerns the soul, less to be cared for, then that which concerns the body? or are we more to value our own damage then the Lords dishonour? We know that no man hath dominion over the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but the Lord that made it exercises his sovereignty therein, and he hath set a law unto the spirits of men, after the rule whereof they are to order both their judgements and affections, and hath given power to those whom he cloathes with Authority,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164912:4"/>which they are to exercise in these things so farre as they are manifested in expressions and actions unto the dishonour of his name, and hurt and prejudice of others. All those who have their senses in any measure exercised in the Word of God, will acknowledge that it is repugnant thereto, that any who are cloathed with power Aeconomick, Ecclesiastick, or politick, should connive at any errour in any of those that are subject to their jurisdiction, or allow it liberty by a law. <hi>Abraham</hi> did command his children and his houshold to keep the way of the Lord, to doe justice and judgement, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>Iacob</hi> took order for purging of his houshold and all that were with him, from all the Idols and strange gods that were amongst them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2. <hi>David</hi> will have none of those who tell lies, but such as walk in a perfect way to be in his house, <hi>Psal.</hi> 101. And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> will have all Pastors and Deacons to rule their houses well, and to keep them in subjection, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. Neither is there lesse required of those that bear charge in the house of God. It was a special part of the office of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his sons to seperate betwixt the pretious and the vile: <hi>Iehojada</hi> set Porters at the gates of the house of the Lord, that none who was unclean in any thing should enter therein, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.19. The Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> would not give place unto those, by subjection, who came in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily to spie out their Churches liberty, for the space of an hour, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.5. And he will have an heretick after the first and second admonition to be rejected, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10. And are not some of the Churches of <hi>Asia</hi> commended for their diligence, and others of them reproved for their negligence herein? <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.2, 6, 14, 15. &amp; 20. And though the power of the Magistrate be herein most questioned by the Patrons of Toleration, yet is the Scripture very clear and plentifull, both in precepts and presidents, in promises and rewards, in threathings and judgements, in encouragements and reproofs, that it is the office and duty of the Magistrate, not only to suppresse and punish iniquity and unrighteousnesse, but also ungodlinesse and errour, and that he beareth the sword in relation to both, as the Lord by his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Moses</hi> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. requires of him that shall raign over his people, that he have a copy of the Law of the Lord by him, and that he reade therein all the daies of his life, that he may learn
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:164912:4"/>to fear the Lord his God, and to keep all the words of that Law: So in the 13. of that book he gives a command to put to death the false Prophet, and the brother that speaketh to his people to turn them away from the Lord their God: and the reasons taken from the nature of the duty, whereby he perswades unto the obedience thereof, are perpetuall and no lesse binding unto us now then to them of old: how strongly doth the Lord plead in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. against Toleration and false worship, and all the occasions thereof, and provocations and irritaments thereto, and how severe is he about the removing and destroying of all these, and in tying all his people in one way, according to the rule of his word, and what peremptory commands are there given unto them concerning both? Was not the blasphemer stoned to death <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.10. It was the great care and singular commendation of <hi>Joshua, Samuel, David, Asa, Iebosaphat, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah, Iosiah, Ezra, Nehemiah, Zerubbabel,</hi> and of such as judged or raigned well in <hi>Israel</hi> or <hi>Iudah,</hi> that they preserved Religion and Reformation in integrity, restored it when it was fallen and corrupted, by destroying Idolatry, and establishing the pure Ordinances of God. <hi>Asa</hi> made a covenant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Iudah</hi> to seek the Lord God of their Fathers 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 14. <hi>Iehosaphat</hi> went out throughout the people from <hi>Beersheba</hi> to mount <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and brought them back unto the Lord God of their Fathers 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19. <hi>Iosiah</hi> made a covenant, and made the people to stand to it 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.32. And the children of <hi>Iudah</hi> after their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> made a covenant, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a curse and into an oath to walk in Gods law, and to observe and doe all the commandements of the Lord their God <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.38.10.29. It is left as a note of perpetuall infamy upon <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> that he caused <hi>Israel</hi> to sin, by erecting the Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and suffering the people to go a whoring after the same. And as it was the cause of the destruction of his house, so at last of the exterminion of <hi>Israel.</hi> And it is severall times observed by the holy Ghost as a fault in severall of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> that the high places were not taken away, and <hi>Judah</hi> it self was also many times sore plagued of God, and at last car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into captivity, because of their tolerating of errour and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. And whoso well pondereth the story of <hi>Iosephus</hi> the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164912:5"/>writer, will finde that both in divine and politick considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Toleration of divers sects amongst them was a main cause of their ruine.</p>
            <p>Some say that the coercive power of the Magistrate, had place in the old Testament, because of an infallible judgement of direction that was alwaies pres<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt with them in the <hi>Ʋrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> for applying of the Law to those who were guilty; But besides that this overthroweth all Ecclesiastick as well as civill censures under the new Testament, as supposing the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of an infallible direction to the right proceeding unto a Sentence against a Blasphemer or a Heretick. What needed then any judiciall processe or the Testimony of witnesses against such? This argues that the procedure was to be in an ordinary way according to a known standing Law: as in cases of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table. And it hath as little strength, that the Magistrate then did these things, not as a Magistrate but as a type of Jesus Christ, seeing the Kings of the heathen such as <hi>Artaxerxes, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> and <hi>Darius</hi> made decrees hereabouts, whose practice is commended by the spirit of God. And some know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other shift, would have the old Testament laid aside in all the question, and have proofs only from the new; But did not the Prophets of old foretell that there should be such a thing under the new Testament. <hi>Zachary</hi> in his 13. chapt. telleth that in the day when the Fountain shall be opened to the house of <hi>David</hi> for sin and for uncleannesse: The Prophet that speaketh lies in the name of the Lord shall not live but be thrust thorow. And as Jesus Christ commands us to beware of false Prophets; <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> to mark them who cause di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. And wisheth that those who trouble the Churches of <hi>Galatia</hi> were cut off, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12. So the same A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. tels us, that the Magistrate is the Minister of God, a Revenger to execute wrath upon those that doe evill. Neither is this wrath confined to the deeds of unrighteousnesse, and these things only that are prejudiciall unto men, and trouble the peace of the common-wealth; but is also to be extended to these things that are dishonourable to God and the peace of the Church; For it cannot be shown that any part of that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which Magistrates had under the old Testament is repealed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164912:5"/>under the new; Neither can any convincing reason be brought why it should be of narrower extent now nor then; Are not blasphemies, heresies and errours dishonourable unto God and destructive unto souls, as well now as of old? And are not men as prone to runne unto those things, and have they not need of as many remedies and restraints now as of old? Nay, be not these evill works as well as the works of injustice and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse? they are high transgressions against the first and great commandement of the Law. And <hi>Moses</hi> speaking of the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, cals them the evil which we are to put away from amongst us, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.5. And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> desires us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of men that are polluted there with as evill workers <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.2. And the same Apostle cals them evill men and seducers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. And the Apostle <hi>John</hi> cals their works evill deeds, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. Therefore if liberty be granted in these, we know no cause why men that can in a handsome way pretend Conscience for it, should be denied liberty to run into excesse and ryot: and to commit all sort of uncleanesse, and practise all wickednesse with greedinesse, which makes us the lesse to wonder that it is propounded that nothing may be punished with death but Murther. Thus far doe the principles of Libertines leade them, that the most monstruous and unnaturall abominations that can be, are not to be punished with death: Neither belike should murther be excepted, If the carnall desire of the preservation of naturall life did not leade them to it. We know not with what words of wonder and astonishment to expresse our selves upon these things. Passe over to the Isles of <hi>Chittim,</hi> and see and send unto <hi>Kedar,</hi> and consider diligently, and see if such a thing hath been heard of, of old, or of late amongst the most brutish and barbrrous nations, such a cursed Toleration as this will not only make every thing in Religion appear to be uncertain, rend the Churches, and disturb the State, and trample all Ordinances Order and Government under foot, and bring forth many blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies and abominations: but is like to banish Religion and righteousnesse quite out of the land, and at last to make a hell upon earth.</p>
            <p>And the thing in it self is not more strange unto us then that those who have lifted up their hands unto heaven, and sworn
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:164912:6"/>before God, Angels and men, to extirpate Popery, heresy, errour, schism, superstition, idolatry and prophanenesse, and whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is contrary to sound doctrine, and the power of godlinesse, and who do so much pretend unto holinesse, and have been made partakers of so many mercies and deliverances, should have so far forgotten the oath and covenant of God as to plead for and proclaim a liberty unto all these things. The solemn League and Covenant was in the beginning amongst all the means that could be thought of, lookt upon and entertain'd as the strongest bulwark of Religion, and surest foundation of a lasting union and peace betwixt the Kingdomes, and the best way for bringing down the enemies of both, and being confirmed by the oath of God cannot be repealed nor altered by any power or authority on earth, but obligeth both Kingdomes unto all the duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, which makes us to wonder that men should be so unhappily bold, as to sport with the oath of God, and mock the Almighty, who is a severe avenger of all such things. And albeit we have no cause to repent of covenanting with <hi>England,</hi> as having done a necessary duty, and laid the foundation of a glorious work, which we trust shall be perfected mangre all the opposition of men, and that we resolve to adhere unto that so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant as long as we live; yet we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to complain of the exceeding great levity and inconstancy of some of those with whom we had to doe, because of the sad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach that is thereby brought upon the cause of God, and the great prejudice that doth thereby redound to the kingdome of his sonne Jesus Christ. Neither is it the least part of our grief that as a Throne is set up for Satan, and the house of God laid wast, so the civill government is exceedingly shaken, if not quite subverted and overthrown. We plead not for Tyranny or arbitrary power either in Kings or Parliaments, neither are we to own or instifie any man in his sinne: but we may remember what adversaries have many times cast upon both Kingdomes, and what both have oftner then once printed and publishrd to the world for their vindication in this: And if after so many publick professions and solemn attestations to the contrary, the foundation shall be razed, Monarchy be destroied, and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments subverted by an imaginary and pretended Agreement of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164912:6"/>the people; as it would destroy the league and covenant, and cause the adversary to blaspheme and insult, so it cannot but be the cause of many miseries and calamities to these Kingdomes. If power be originally in the people, and all of them do equally share in the priviledge of liberty and freedome; how comes it to passe that a few take upon them to impose this Agreement upon others, and that it is desired that the opposers may be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with death? Let it be yeelded that some at first may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descend upon the modell without the knowledge of the whole body: yet when it is offered unto them, what if the one half or the greater part shall refuse to consent or submit thereto? shall they be compelled by others to do it, and destroyed if they will not obey? Is not this to take power over those that have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quill power with themselves, and to encroach upon the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of those who are as free as themselves? If it be said that they do but impose in things necessary that concern common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and freedome; we demand who are Judges of these things? Have not these who refuse, as much power and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to judge as these who would impose it upon them? And if they judge it to be contrary to their freedome, who can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll them herein, without encroaching thereupon, and offering violence to their consciences, who may conceive such a way neither to suit with Religion nor righteousnesse? And to speak nothing of the troubles that are like to arise otherwise; may not this open again the issues of bloud, and imbroyl the land in a new war, betwixt these who shall refuse, and these who shall impose such a model, wherein men may happily lose both themselves and their liberty, whilest they seek to be too much free? Were it not better to preserve Monarchy and the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, walking in the middle, betwixt Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Anarchie, betwixt arbitrary Government and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion?</p>
            <p>We know that such a way is looked upon by some as the best foundation of safety, but we know nothing more like to bring ruine and destruction; And therefore pitying those who are gone out of the way, we do from the compassion which we have to their souls, earnestly and in the name of the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech all these in <hi>England</hi> who plead for Toleration, the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164912:7"/>aside of the Covenant, and change of the civill government. To consider these things impartially, 1. What fair professions and promises were made unto this Kingdome to perswade them to join in covenant with <hi>England,</hi> and how often before and since that time, these things have been renewed by Letters, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations and Remonstrances unto these in this land, Petitions to the King, Ordinances of the Houses, and letters to the Churches abroad, all this is still upon record, and will bear witnesse before the Lord and unto the following generations against the levity, perversenes and perjury of those who have sworn the League and Covenant, and gad so much about to change their way. 2. That the League and Covenant was the first Foundation of their victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and successe, and of the ruine of the Malignant party in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> We need not put them in minde at what low ebb the Parliaments Forces were at the contriving thereof, and how soon the Lord gave Testimony from heaven by a victory over the enemy of his approbation of the same, and how from that day forward they prospered, and the enemy fell before them still. 3. That the Lord hath all waies been a severe avenger of the breaches of oaths and covenants personall, and which concernes the things of men, much more Nationall, and which concerns the things of God. 4. That never any perverted the truth and corrupted the worship of God and prospered. 5. What shall be the advantage, nay, how great shall be the losse of all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of bloud and of pains that these Kingdomes have been at, if for all this we shall reap nothing but Toleration and confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Have we laboured in the fire to remove one corrupt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to bring in many in its stead? to put down Tiranny, and set up Anarchy. 6. Whether this be such a Testimony of gratitude as the Lord cals for at their hands in lien of all his mercies, and giving unto them victory over all their enemies? 7. Whether such things beseem those who would be called Saints, and pretend to be for the Lord, and use his name in all their professions and undertakings? 8. Whether such proceedings doe not bring a sad reproach and heavy imputation upon the work of God in these Kingdoms? In nothing doth the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish, Prelaticall and Malignant party more insult; And, is it a light matter to cause the enemy to blaspheam?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:164912:7"/>9. How sore the weak are stumbled, and the hearts of the godly throughout all the Protestant Churches wounded? We have suffered many things, but nothing so heavy to our spirits as this. 10. If such a way be not contrary to the whole strain of Gods Word, and to the practice of all the Saints since the beginning of the world unto this day, 11. What shall be the end of these things, and the many sad and dolefull consequences that shall follow thereupon? If from these and the like considerations any be moved to take warning to desist from the evil of their way, we shall therein rejoyce, and glorifie God in their behalf; but if they shall refuse to hearken, we have discharged our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and in the name of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whose ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants we are, we doe dissent from, and protest against such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, as destructive to Religion, the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the work of uniformity, and the civil Government, and shall wait for the salvation of the Lord.</p>
            <p>In the next place albeit we doe not desire to adde sorrow unto any mans affliction, but rather if any suffer for righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse sake to comfort him, yet we were not, faithfull, if we did not put our Brethren in <hi>England</hi> in minde of their sloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse and negligence in the Lords work, that in this day of their trouble they may be humbled because of their want of zeal for God and his Cause. The Lord hath put into the hands of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> many pretious opportunites and fair occasions to have extirpate popery, errour, heresie, schism and prophanenesse, and to have established Reformation, and the Government of the House of God. Many Petitions and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations from many in <hi>England,</hi> and Declarations, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strances and letters from the Parliament and generall Assembly, and their Commissioners in this Land, were tendered unto them concerning this thing: Yet notwithstanding of all these, did they still suffer the House of God to lie waste, and the evil to grow, which had been easily resisted in the beginning, but now is gone over the face of the Land like a floud, and hath troden under foot their own power and authority. It hath been the Lords way in carrying on of his work, to stain the pride of all glory, and to break and put down all these powers that have not exalted himself, and promoved the Kingdome of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:164912:8"/>Son. And though we doe not justifie these insolent attempts upon the Houses, yet we cannot but desire the Members to behold the hand of the most high, and to read their sin engraven upon their judgement. It is a righteous thing with the Lord to abase all these that will not honour him: The Lord certainly hath a great controversie against them, for encroaching upon the royall Scepter of Jesus Christ, and denying unto him any externall Government over his House, but such as is dependent upon them, by assuming unto themselves the ultimate decision of all Ecclesiastick causes and censures. And doubtlesse the Lord is also highly displeased with their proceedings in the Treaty at <hi>Newport,</hi> in reference to Religion and Covenant, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which they accepted of such concessions from his Majesty, as being acquiesced in, were dangerous and destructive to both. We wish they may now at last see their oversight and failing in these things, and be men of wisdom to hear the voice of the rod, and who hath appointed it: If their soul be humbled for their sin, and if they shall take upon them the vows of God, for giving unto Jesus Christ his due, and doing whatsoever is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the God of heaven for the house of the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who knows but the Lord may take away the reproach, and restore them to their dignity and power?</p>
            <p>And though we doubt not, but many in <hi>England</hi> have these years past mourned for the desolation of the House of God, and for the rise and grouth of so many errours in that Land, and have poured forth their supplications before the Lord for a remedy of these things. And that we are not ignorant what a considerable number of Ministers have done in their Sermons and printed Books and Testimonies; yet we shall desire all that love truth and holinesse in that Land, to consider whether they have so timeously, and with that courage and zeal that was convenient, appeared for the Lord, and acquit themselves in their duty, in reference to Religion, and the Solemn League and Covenant. And if any finde themselves faulty, to mourn for it and to pray for mercy, and more of the spirit of Christ, that they may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be more faithfull, and doe their duty boldly and without fear. As many in <hi>England</hi> mourned with us in the day of our distresse before the Lord in our behalf, so we, and all the godly in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:164912:8"/>this Land, pour forth to God our supplications in private and in publike for them: And albeit we will not take upon us to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe, yet as the servants of the living God, who have obtained mercy in some measure to be faithfull, and have found such a way to be profitable among our selves. We exhort all our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>England</hi> to acknowledge their iniquities before the Lord, especially the breaches of that Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which was so publickly sworn before God, Angels and men, and to renew their oath and vows in his sight, which we doubt not, if gone about in sincerity, shall be attended with a blessing &amp; success from heaven. It hath been the Lords dispensation in these Kingdoms for the most part, to leave a branch of hope in the one Kingdom, when the other was like to perish, and to suffer ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to grow to a great height of insolency and power, and then to bring them down. And therefore albeit the flouds lift up their voice and make a noise, yet we know no cause why the Lords people should wax faint, or cast away their confidence. The Lord on high is mightier then the noise of many waters, yea, then the mighty waves of the sea: his word is established in heaven, and his Testimonies are very sure: and beside the many great and pretious promises which he hath given unto us, and his goodnesse to his Saints of old, he hath furnished his people in these Lands, with so many experiences of his mighty hand and stretched out arm working salvation and delivery for them, that it were a shame for any amongst them to wax faint, and not to believe. For, <hi>Yet a little while he that shall come will come and will not tarry.</hi> Now the just shall live by faith, but if any man draw back, his soul shall have no pleasure in him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:164912:9"/>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:164912:9"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At Edinburgh,</hi>
                  <date>Jan. 18. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>The returne of the Estates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the Testimony communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto them, by the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the General Assembly, and their Concurrence with the same.</head>
            <p>THe Estates of Parliament presently conveened, taking into their most serious consideration, the seasonable Testimony against Toleration, and the present Proceedings of the Sectaries and their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors in <hi>England,</hi> in reference to Religion and Government, with an Admonition and Exhortation to their brethren there, from the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to them by you; And pondering the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent sad and strange condition of affairs in their Neighbour Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> represented there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and in severall other Papers come to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: They do returne unto you their hearty thankes, both for your good correspondence, (which this Parliament doth with all cheerfulnesse entertaine,) and for your great care and faithfulnesse, in giving such necessary and seasonable warnings and testimonies against the dangers of the times, on all hands, at all occasions: And do heartily concurre in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:164912:10"/>the grounds thereof, against Toleration, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Proceedings of Sectaries in <hi>England,</hi> in reference to Religion and Government, and in the admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and encouragements so fully expressed in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: And do most willingly adde this our Testimony thereunto, that our brethren of <hi>England</hi> may be the more moved, by the mouth of two witnesses, and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially such, as together with them stand and fall; and are covenanted with them for mutnall good, that they may lay these things to heart, and abstaine from all such sinfull and dangerous courses, and that the faithfull may not faint under these afflictions, nor omit any necessary testimony or duty against the corruptions of the time. And because there hath been severall aspersions published in printed Pamphlets, for the strengthning of the hands of those who go on in these sinfull wayes, and for discouraging of the hearts of those who are suffering under them: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Estates of Parliament after diligent enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all the Members of this Parliament, upon their publike and solemne Oath, concerning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and others, do declare and assure their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>England,</hi> That they cannot find that either this Kingdome or any Person therein, had any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of, or accession to the late Proceedings of the English Army, or relation to the Kings Person, or the Houses, or restrained Members thereof: But are very confident that there is no ground for such asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. On the other hand, so soon as this Parliament was conveened and constituted, and heard of the present posture of affairs, they being no wayes sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with their proceedings, and the reasons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:164912:10"/>published to the world; and being convinced of the dangerous consequences, and calamities likely to follow thereupon; They gave present instructions to their Commissioners, founded upon the Obligations and Declarations made between, and by both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes (of which the matter of fact is fully expressed in the Paper given in by our Commissioners, <hi>Jan.</hi> the 6. instant, to the Speaker of the House of Commons, in our name, and according to our mind, which is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with communicated unto you,) to presse a delay of all these proceedings against the Kings Person, the the Princes right of Succession, or the fundamentall Government of the Kingdome, untill this Kingdome should present their interest and desires; and in case of their proceeding therein, that they should declare in the name of this kingdome their dissent; and protest, that as this nation is free from all knowledge of, or accesson to these designes and practices, so they may be free of all the calamities, miseries and confusions which may follow thereupon to these di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted Kingdomes. And as our constant resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and earnest desire to preserve inviolably the peace and union betwixt the Kingdomes, will evidently appeare to any, who will read (besides all our former actions and sufferings for it,) our act of approving the indiction of this present Parliament, and our act repealing all past in the last Parliament or Committee of Estates for the late unlawfull engagement against <hi>England;</hi> And as yee are witnesses of our keeping a solemne day of humiliation, not only for our owne sinnes and miseries, but also for the sins and distresses lying on our deare brethren, and for seeking the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:164912:11"/>Lords direction to us, that we may know and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all the duties which the Lord requires of us, at such a time, after such judgements and deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on his part, and such an acknowledgement and renewed Covenant on our part, not only in relation to our owne affairs at home, but also to what may concerne Religion, King and Kingdomes, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the solemne League and Covenant in these u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Nations: So we declare that it is our constant resolution, (with Gods assistance,) to give all season<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Testimonies, and do all necessary duties within our power and calling, for the prersevation, of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun Reformation against Toleration of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of the fundamental Government, against A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy and confusion, and for continuing and preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the peace and union between the Kingdomes, and all the bonds thereof, so often acknowledged and expressed in their Treaties; especially for one King, one Covenant, one Religion; and for the observance of the manifold Declarations, emitted between and by both Kingdomes to the world, in the positive and necessary duties, for the pursuance of all the ends of the solemne League and Covenant. And to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect we are and shall be most ready, to deale and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpose with all earnestnesse and sincerity of heart, and by all lawfull and necessary means, with all whom it may concerne for setling truth and peace in these Kingdomes, upon the grounds and Propositions, so often agreed unto, and so long insisted upon by these two Nations, and upon what further shall be found safe and necessary for the removing of these distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and preventing new issues of bloud, calamities
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:164912:11"/>and confusions in these Kingdomes: Which the searcher of hearts knoweth to be the earnest desire, and firme resolution of this Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Extractum de libris actorum Parliamenti per me Dominum Willielmum Scot de Clarkingtone militem, Clericum Parliamenti.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. Scot. Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Right Reverend, their Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved Brethren, the Ministers of the Gospel, in the Province of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend and wel-beloved in our Lord Jesus,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF our soules were not grieved at the calamitous condition, and sad pressures, wherewith the Lord, who hath his fire in Zion, and his furnace in <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> hath afflicted you; We could not, but be under the woe pronounced by the mouth of the Lord, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst those that are at ease in Zion, and remember not the affliction of <hi>Joseph.</hi> Yea, we conceive it our duty, to testify our brotherly condolency and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion toward you, as being in bonds with you and desirous through our fellow-feeling to share with you in those remnants of the afflictions of Christ; and in our approaches to the Throne of Grace, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your sufferings, with Fasting and Teares.</p>
            <p>And as we are confident, that the Lord choiseth his own in the furnace; so doth he make way through all these confusions, that this Island of <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> may be at length, a Crown of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a Royall Diadem in the hand of our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:164912:12"/>God; And, as we conceive, this is the time, in which, the Lord calleth you to give a second publike testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to his truth, against all the errours and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the time, since now he pleadeth with that Nation for breach of Covenant, as of old he did with his people: Turne O backsliding children, saith the Lord, for I am marryed unto you; and I will take you, one of a City, and two of a family, and I will bring you to Zion. And as one part of the Iland hath renewed the Covenant with God; So he calleth the other part, and you in particular of that City, to go before the rest of the Land, in the same duty, and to be strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, in pleading for the establishing of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of his Sonne Christ by Assemblies and Presbyteries, that so you may build the old waste places, and repaire the desolations of many Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. We need not put you in mind, that the incursions of the wild Boares of the Forrest, upon the Vineyard of the Lord, cannot but flow from the not setting up of the Hedge of Discipline; And that when in the Kirk of Christ, there is not one Lord, one Faith, one Baptisme, there must arise many false Christs, and false Prophets, in so much that (if it were possible) they should deceive the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Elect. As therefore (dearely beloved in the Lord) your Testimony formerly given was to us, and to the Reformed Kirks, no lesse refreshing, then the rain upon the new mowen grasse; So give us leave to beseech you in the Lord Jesus, since the eyes of the Lord are upon you, and Angels and men, and all the Reformed Kirks in the World, are witnesses of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:164912:12"/>your actions and sufferings, to acquit your selves, the Ambassadours of Jesus Christ; and without fear of men, or fainting in this day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> trouble, to give seasonable warning to all the kingdome, of the sad and dang rous consequences of irreligious and licentious Toleration of all Religions, the Idoll of Indignation in that land, that provoketh the eyes of his glory; of the horrible blasphemies, heresies and errors now abounding in the land; of altering the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and wel-established Government of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; of Anarchy, abolishing of Magistracy, the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ordinance of God; which we cannot but look on as the beginning of woes, a seminary of all vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, injustice and oppressions, the continuing and increasing of the troubles of <hi>Britaine,</hi> the utter dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solving of all humane societies, the ruine of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Nation and Kirk; and, which is most fearfull, the displaying of a Banner against the Lord, and the kindling of his wrath against the Land, which shall burne to the bottome of hell; as our Testimony (which we have sent unto you,) doth we trust in some part discover, and is well known to your selves.</p>
            <p>We are confident (deare Brethren,) that you minde the precious promises of the Lord, made to those who keep the word of his patience, that they shall be kept from the houre of tentation, which shall come on all the world to try them that dwell upon the earth. And we cannot but out of our owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence shew you, how the Lord hath been graciously pleased to carry us through, against the powers of the disaffected Party of this Kingdome, who indeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no lesse then the casting down of all we builded
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:164912:13"/>these years past; and that it is now our joy &amp; consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the Lord did disappoint them, uphold us, &amp; make good the word of his weak servants, who desire to be faithful in his Cause &amp; Covenant. There should be cause, we acknowledge, to fear their fear, and to be couraged, if we were not perswaded that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, Favourers and Abettors of these Blasphemies and impure Heresies, had indicted warre against the Lord and his Christ. But since the Lord of Hosts is with you, we hope as his high Name is ingaged in this Covenant and cause, neither <hi>Babylon</hi> nor <hi>Edom</hi> shall prevaile; but as the Lord hath shaken the Throne of Anti-christ, so will he lay waste the mountaine of <hi>Edom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore being confident that the Lord shall make you stedfast, unmoveable, alwayes abounding in the work of the Lord, and shall encourage you to renew the Covenant with the Lord: We humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech the God of peace that brought againe from the dead our Lord Jesus, that great shepherd of the sheep, through the blood of the everlasting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to make you perfect in every good work, to do his Will, working in you that which is wel-pleasing in his sight, through Jesus Christ. We are</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Brethren and Servants<lb/> in the Lord, the Commissioners<lb/> of the Generall Assembly.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinburgh,</hi>
                  <lb/>
                  <date>18. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Subscribed in our name and at our command,<lb/> by Mr. <hi>Robert Dowglas,</hi> Moderatour.</signed> Delivered to the Ministers at <hi>Sion-Colledge, Jan.</hi> 26. by the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Commissioners of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>